Guide to the Alf Engen ski video collection 1938-2004
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
Alf Engen ski video collection
1938-2004
University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections Audio Visual Archives Special Collections 295 South 1500 East Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860 (801) 581-8864
A0391
Engen, Alf, 1909-1997
17 16mm films, 65 VHS videocassettes, 39 U-Matic videocassettes, 14 Betacam videocassettes
The Alf Engen ski video collection (1938-2004) contains footage that reveals the evolution of the sport of skiing and of ski facilities and resorts, including news reports and interviews featuring Engen and footage Engen competeing in National Championship events, instructing ski school, and skiing with family and friends. Alf Engen was an internationally recognized Nordic and Alpine skier instrumental in the development of the ski industry in Utah and the American West.
Biographical Note
Alf Engen (1909-1997) was born in Mjondallen, Norway, the oldest of three boys. Engen's father died when he was only nine years old, but he had already implemented the joy of skiing into the hearts of his sons, Alf, Sverre and Corey (Kaare). The boys learned to ski jump at a young age and became well known for thier Nordic ability in their homeland.
In 1929 Engen immigrated to the United States with his younger brother, Sverre. They Initialy settled in Chicago where they joined the American-Norwegian Athletic Club. He and several club members traveled to Westby, Wisconsin to participate in a ski jumping meet. With his first jump in the Westby Nordic event, Engen broke the world's record for distance ski jumping and was invited to tour the North American Nordic circuit with professional jumpers.
In 1931 he settled in Salt Lake City, Utah. His youngest brother, Corey, and their mother immigrated to the United States in 1933 and the three Engen Brothers travled the United States as professional jumpers, breaking Nordic records and gaining recognition everywhere they went.
In 1937, Engen married Evelyn Pack, regained his amateur standing, and ranked among the top Nordic skiers in the world. He helped in planning and developing around thirty ski areas in Utah, Nevada, Idaho, and Wyoming while working for the United States Forest Service as a winter sports advisor. In 1938 he was invited to represent the Sun Valley Ski Club in Nordic jumping. While living in Idaho, he taught himself how to Alpine ski and spent time off the slopes preforming in several movies and newreels. In 1940, he finished first in the National Four-way in Seattle, Washington.
Engen assisted with the operation and ski lessons at Alta and Snow Basin Ski Schools during the 1945-46 ski season and later returned to Utah to direct the Alta Ski School, the Little Mountain Ski School, and the Deseret News Free Ski School after coaching the United States Olympic Ski Team in 1948. He received the Skier's Hall of Fame Award in 1956.
Alf Engen died in 1997 at the age of 88.
The Alf Engen ski video collection (1938-2004) contains footage that reveals the evolution of the sport of skiing and of ski facilities and resorts, including news reports and interviews featuring Engen and footage Engen competeing in National Championship events, instructing ski school, and skiing with family and friends.
The materials are arranged by format type.
Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.
See also the Alf Engen scrapbooks (Accn 1006), Corey Engen scrapbooks (Accn 1401), the Ski Museum records (Accn 518) and the Alan K. Engen ski video collection (A0402) and papers (Accn 1601).
Engen, Alan K.; Engen, Sverre; Alf Engen Ski School; Deseret News Ski School; Alta (Utah); Skis and skiing--United States--History--Sources; Skis and skiing--Utah--History--Sources; Sports and Recreation; Moving Images; Moving images
- Engen family skiing, 1950-1960; 16mm film, VHS videocassette, U-matic videocassette, Betacam videocassette Silent, color (Reel 1)
- Engen family skiing, 1960s; 16mm film, VHS videocassette, U-matic videocassette Silent, color (Reel 2)
- Alta ski jumps, 1969; 16mm film, VHS videocassette, U-matic videocassette, Betacam videocassette Sound, color (Reel 3)
- North American Ski Instructors conference, 1970; 16mm film, VHS videocassette, U-matic videocassette, Betacam videocassette Sound, color (Reel 4)
- Sports Club: Alf Engen skiing, 1976; 16mm film, VHS videocassette, U-matic videocassette, Betacam videocassette Sound, black and white (Reel 5)
  Engen demonstrates basic ski technique and maneuvering tricks.
- National Four-Way Championship, 1940; 16mm film, VHS videocassette, U-matic videocassette, Betacam videocassette Silent, color (Reel 6)
- Ski gulls, undated; 16mm film, VHS videocassette, U-matic videocassette, Betacam videocassette Sound, black and white (Reel 7)
  Early skiing.
- Ultra powder, 16mm film, VHS videocassette, Betacam videocassette Sound, color (Reel 8)
  Alf Engen and others skiing untracked powder.
- Summer skiing at Mt. Baldy, California, 1959; 16mm film, VHS videocassette, U-matic videocassette, Betacam videocassette Sound, black and white (Reel 9)
- Peruvian Lodge film, 1960; 16mm film, VHS videocassette, U-matic videocassette, Betacam videocassette Sound, color (Reel 10)
  Promotional film for the Alta Peruvian lodge narrated by American ski legends Lowell Thomas, Alf Engen, Alan Engen, Stein Erickson, Buddy Wagner, and Junior Bounous.
- Peruvian Lodge film, 1970; 16mm film, VHS videocassette, U-matic videocassette, Betacam videocassette Silent, color (Reel 11)
- Alf and Alan Engen skiing, 1950s; 16mm film, VHS videocassette, U-matic videocassette, Betacam videocassette Sound, color (Reel 12)
  Alf Engen skiing with his son Alan Engen.
- Old Sun Valley, 1950-1960; 16mm film, VHS videocassette, U-matic videocassette, Betacam videocassette Silent, color (Reel 13)
  Various people skiing and at Sun Valley Resort in Idaho as well as races held at the resort.
- National Jumping Championship, 1938; 16mm film, VHS videocassette, U-matic videocassette, Betacam videocassette Silent, color (Reel 14)
- Alf and Alan skiing at Alta, 16mm film, VHS videocassette, U-matic videocassette, Betacam videocassette Silent, color (Reel 15)
  Alf Engen skiing with his son, Alan Engen at the Alta Ski Resort in Utah's Wasatch Mountains.
- Alf Engen Ski School, undated; 16mm film, VHS videocassette, U-matic videocassette, Betacam videocassette Sound, black and white (Reel 16)
- Snow trails, 1940-1950; 16mm film, VHS videocassette, U-matic videocassette Sound, black and white (Reel 17)
- White ecstacy: the ski chase, undated; U-matic videocassettes (Cassette 18)
- Dr. Quakenbush skis the headwall, undated; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 19)
- Skiing with Alf Engen and family, U-matic videocassette (Cassette 20)
- Alta: the first fifty years, undated; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 21)
- Legends of American skiing 1849-1940, undated; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 22)
- National Broadcasting Company (NBC): Alf Engen and Mike Lenard, 1984; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 23)
- National Broadcasting Company (NBC): Alf Engen, 1992; U-matic videocassette, VHS videocassette (Cassette 24)
  This news story, focused on Alf Engen, examines his career as an athlete and ski instructor, then shifts to Engen's experience with injuries. The segment also shows Engen skiing at age 85.
- Larry Warren interview: Alf Engen at Bear Hollow, undated; U-matic videocassette, Betacam videocassette, VHS videocassette (Cassette 25)
- Keith West interview: Alf Engen at Alan Engen's home, undated; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 26)
- Ski riders of the Wasatch, undated; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 27)
- Skiing the American way, undated; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 28)
- Eighth Interski, undated; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 29)
- Mike Lenard interview: Alf Engen, 1992; U-matic videocassette, VHS videocassette, Betacam videocassette (Cassette 30)
- Alta's 50th anniversary Gelande, undated; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 31)
- Alan Engen footage, undated; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 32)
- The white badge, undated; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 33)
- Sixth Interski, undated; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 34)
- National Ski Academy (NSA) certification directors meeting, 1959; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 35)
- Playtime Journey newsreel: First Deseret News Ski School, Ecker Hill ski jumping, undated; U-matic videocassette, VHS videocassett (Cassette 36)
- For the love of skiing: a snapshot of early Alta ski history, undated; VHS videocassettes, Betacam videocassette (Cassette 37)
- Alf Engen: an American ski legend, undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 38)
  The annals of ski jumping and powder snow come to life in this eighteen minute snapshot of skiing pioneer, Alf Engen. Narrated by his son, Alan Engen, this presentation shows Alf, America's 20th century "Renaissance Skier" as: Former World Ski Jumping Champion, winner of 16 U.S National Skiing Championship Titles, U.S. Olympic Team Coach, "Father of the powder skiing technique", Ski Area designer, and instructor to hundreds of thousands of skiers.
  Special Collections holds limited edition #1/100 of this movie as well as autographed 3/4" videocassettes and 16mm films.
- Alta photo and video: Alf Engen Ski School awards, Alta Peruvian Lodge banquet, 1994 April 17; VHS videocassette (Cassette 39)
  Emeritus awards: Wally Mears and Bob "Pepi" Smith
  Hall of fame: Evelyn Engen.
- Construction of the Joe Quinney Winter Sports Center and Alf Engen Ski Museum, undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 40)
- Wolfgang Lert ski memories, undated; VHS videocassette (Cassette 41)
- Rasmussen art unveiling, 2004 January 23; VHS videocassette (Cassette 42)
- Park City, Ski, undated; Betacam videocassette (Cassette 43)
  The Park City film contains footage of old Park City and various interviews pertaining to the future development of the area.
  The Ski film contains footage of early development of Park City Ski Area. It also contains footage of ski racing.